<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumph of faith A very godly, fruitfull and comfortable treatise on Rom. 8. verse 37. Penned by Daniel Ienkinson Master in Arts, late of Emmanuel Coll. in Cambridge, and found in his studie at the time of his death.</title>
            <author>[Jenkinson, Daniel].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839336</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839336</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04380)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 840:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumph of faith A very godly, fruitfull and comfortable treatise on Rom. 8. verse 37. Penned by Daniel Ienkinson Master in Arts, late of Emmanuel Coll. in Cambridge, and found in his studie at the time of his death.</title>
                  <author>[Jenkinson, Daniel].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Griffin for Sam. Macham, and are to be solde at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Bull-head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3745:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Triumph of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A VERY GODLY, fruitfull and comfortable <hi>Treatiſe on</hi> ROM. 8. verſe 37.</p>
            <p>Penned by <hi>Daniel Ienkinſon</hi> Master in Arts, late of  <hi>EMMANVEL</hi> Coll. in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and found in his Studie at the time of his death.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. IOHN 5.4.</bibl>
               <p>This is that victory that hath ouercome this world, euen our faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Edw. Griffin</hi> for <hi>Sam. Macham,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Bull-head. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3745:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3745:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, as it was bountifull loue to his louely <hi>Ionathan,</hi> that moued the ſweet Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Iſrael, King <hi>Dauid,</hi> to ſhow ſuch kindneſſe to <hi>Mephiboſheth, Ionathans</hi> ſonne, as to cauſe him to eat continually at the Kings Table, <hi>2. Sam. 9.13.</hi> ſo it is Chriſtian loue to my deceaſed (loue worthie) Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, that hath mooued me to giue this his obſcured fatherleſſe Orphan, falling into my hands, the best pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment I was able, vz. to liue (as I hope) continually in the houſes, and
<pb facs="tcp:3745:3"/>
ſomtimes hands (and if God bleſſe my wiſh) euen in the harts of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; as yeelding a liuely ſent and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant ſmel of thoſe great Graces which abounded plentifully in the godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: and which too ſoone were nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the bud, and by vntimely death reſtrained from the vſe of the Church, if it may ſo be ſayd without offence to the higheſt Prouidence, vnder cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and condition of his moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous will. If this poore Orphan In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant the legitimate iſſue of a childe in yeeres, but of a man for gifts, and an olde Christian, may chance to pleaſe, and grow acceptable for his fathers ſake, or his owne ſake, where hee may conuerſe; there is ſome hope, that in due time (the Lord permitting) ſome of his Germane brothers may
<pb facs="tcp:3745:3"/>
beare him companie, on this faſhion, as good companions for all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in this wearie pilgrimage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the celeſtiall Canaan, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto both this and the rest do giue true aime, if I take not my aime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe. And ſo hoping, that after the reading heereof, thou wilt confeſſe thy ſelfe the abundant reaper of my Loues fruit, I leaue thee in his watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protection, who alone ſanctifieth all meanes of ſauing knowledge and graces vnto his children, crauing but thy prayers for my paines, and reſting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>one that deſires thy true good vnfainedly <hi>I. A.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:3745:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3745:4"/>
            <head>THE TRIVMPH of Faith.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. Chap. <hi>8.</hi> Ver. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Neuertheleſſe, in all theſe things we are more then conquerours through him that loued vs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words may not vnfitly be termed The tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of Faith, and the glorious vaunt of a reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Chriſtian, grounded vpon the liuely appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Grace, and the infallible
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3745:5"/>
expectance of Glory. Both which the Apo. hauing euinced in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Treatiſe, by inſtances and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aboue exception, he ſteps in, in the thirty and one verſe with an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly challenge, daring defiance to any encounter, diſdaine to any Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant or reſolued Champion, that dare enter the liſts with him and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his challenge. What then ſhall we ſay to theſe things, if God be on our ſide who can be againſt vs? yea Paule indeed tis ſomewhat that yee ſay, if God be on our ſide who can be againſt vs? or if they be againſt vs what hurt can they doe vs? what skills their prowes and oppoſition, though it were the plotting of Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel, or Rabſhekahs reſolution; when as God playes our part, the Lord himſelfe maintaines our qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, againſt whome there is neither wiſdome nor counſell, neither bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily puiſſance nor courage in the day of battel? But how can ye make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3745:5"/>
vs beleeue that God is on our ſide? how may we be perſwaded that we haue ſuch an approued Captaine, of ſo tried a ſtrength, for proweſſe ſo puiſſant? how ſays the Apoſtle? why I will tell you, he ſpared not his only Sonne, but — how ſhall he not with him giue vs all things alſo; yea euen himſelfe which is all in all? he that hath giuen vs his Sonne, the heyre of all things, is it likely that he will deny vs matters of any value, of any conſequence? he that hath giuen vs his Sonne, his ioy, and delight, how is it poſſible that he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vs himſelfe? nay in that he hath giuen vs his Sonne which is his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, he hath giuen vs himſelfe. For where a mans treaſure is, there his heart is, and where his heart is there himſelfe is. Now Chriſt being Gods treaſure, and this treaſure giuen to vs, we may well with Dauid chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the Lord as our owne poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: eſpecially ſith our Chriſt is the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3745:6"/>
treſure-houſe of diuine benediction; of whoſe fulnes we haue al receiued: the worker of attonement and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, that hath made God to be on our ſide, that to fore was auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from vs. We may well therefore exult, and chaunt out thoſe cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full notes of Iſraels ſweet ſinger that diuine Muſitian. The Lord is our light and our ſaluation, whom ſhall we feare? the Lord is the ſtrength of our life, of whom ſhall we be afraid? Heereupon the Apoſtle throwes downe his gauntlet with a challenge to our ſpirituall enemies, to ſee if any of them dare appeare in their likenes or admit of his proffer. But when it will not be, he prouokes them to iudgment. Then, who ſaith he, ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? no body anſwers. Tis God that Iuſtifieth, who ſhal condemne? who dare appeare in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs? If they wil go that way to worke, all is huſht, no body peeps
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3745:6"/>
out. And why I pray you, becauſe we haue ſuch a Captain as none dare meete in the feild: ſuch an Aduocate as none dare oppoſe: ſuch a friend in the court as none dare looke in the face: Chriſt Ieſus, who was dead but is riſen againe with Triumph, ouer the powers of death &amp; of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who now ſitting at the right hand of God, makes requeſt for vs? Yea ſaith the Apoſtle, will none of them apeare? ſhall we haue none anſwere in this kind? weele euen to our former challenge, call them out by their names, and ſee what they will ſay to vs. Ho, ſaith he, who ſhall ſeperate vs from the loue of Chriſt? who dare bee ſo bold as to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take that encounter? what tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or anguiſh, or perſecution? &amp;c. Will you ſay any thing to vs? dare you put in a foot here, yea, I promiſe you Paule now you haue met with your match, theſe fellowes will ſay ſomwhat to you, they will put you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3745:7"/>
to your ſhifts I tell you, for heere we go to the wall, Theſe will not greeue and annoy and purſue vs, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue vs alſo of life, and ſpirits, and leaue vs breathleſſe and liueleſſe and ſouleleſſe: and yet this perill is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitable, that beſides wofull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, tis the verdict and doome of the diuine ſpirit, that for thy ſake are we killed all the day long, wee are euen counted as ſheep to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. What ſay you to this Paul? Do not theſe coole your courage, doe not theſe make you to pull in the head? Do you not thinke that theſe will abalienate you from Chriſt? lay your honour in the duſt, and your hopes in obliuion? Neuer a whit ſayes the Apoſtle, for why ſhould they? why! I will tell you what: All theſe that yee haue named, let them bandy themſelues together, with their beſt forces: let the Deuill be their leader, and bee their warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: all come ruſhing againſt vs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3745:7"/>
with the extremitie of their malice, why they hurt vs not an hayre, they get neuer a foot of ground from vs, neither is our ſpirituall eſtate in any hazard by all their ſtratagems, though they ſpew out the very gall of their bitterneſſe, the height of their malice, though they ſtrike ſtraight downe without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, and make euen a lane before them as they goe, yet neuertheleſſe this is our reioycing, this is our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and our crowne of glory, that the day is ours, the field is won, ours is the conqueſt, for in theſe, yea in all theſe things we are more than conquerors, through him that loued vs. Which words (as you ſee) by the Apoſtles Reioynder to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going challenge vpon a ſuppoſed acceptation, who ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt; Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and anguiſh, &amp;c. they take vpon them the combat, they will bee the men that ſhall doe it? The Apoſtle
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3745:8"/>
hereupon replies, and returnes his ſpeach in a diſiunct propoſition to this purpoſe, Well ſayes he, ſuppoſe that all theſe fellowes, you tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c. doe ſeaze vpon vs, as wee know they may, and doe vs the worſt that they can, as we are ſure they will: for, for thy ſake are wee killed all the day long, we are euen counted as ſheepe to the ſlaughter: neuertheles we haue no cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort: for though we be afflicted on euery ſide, yet are we not in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, though we be in pouertie, yet not thereby ouercome, though we be perſecuted, yet are we not forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, in a word, though wee be caſt downe we periſh not, yea we are ſo far from the foile, that in all theſe things we are more than conquerors through him that loued vs. As if the Apoſtle had ſaid, Suppoſe we be in tribulation, yet tribulation yeelds experience, and experience hope, and hope makes vs not aſhamed, nay
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3745:8"/>
it giues vs confidence and acceſſe with boldneſſe. Say we be in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and that the butchers of Gods Saints get vs into their fingers, yet ſo, that wee reioyce vnder the croſſe and count it a crowne, we are ioyfull in bonds, and deeme them freedome, yea our very ſtripes are the marks of the Lord Ieſus. ô glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious laſhes! Say we be in anguiſh, that that bitter fellow hath laid hold on vs: yet ſo, that though heauineſſe lodge for a night, and will not let vs feele the ſoftneſſe of the pillow, yet ioy comes in the morning, the Lord renuing his mercies. Say we be in nakedneſſe, that we haue neuer a rag on our backs, nor ſo much as an old ſacke to creepe into, yet this is our comfort, that one day we ſhall haue heauenly veſtures, rich robes, and long white garments, ſcarlet with pleaſures &amp; golden abiliments. Say we be in perill, in the extremitie of hazard, yet ſo that in the greateſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3745:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dangers wee expect the Lords deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: with Dauid ready to bee ſlaine, wee comfort our ſelues in our God: with Ionas wee ſeeme to be caſt out of his ſight, yet with the ſame Prophet wee remember his holy temple, his former mercies. In a word, ſay, wee bee vnder the ſword, euen in the iawes and fanges of death, yet this is our rejoycement, that euen in death there is life, death it ſelfe is great gaine, the graue is hie aduantage. For bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord, well therefore may we be ſaid to be Conquerors, yea more then conquerors through him that loued vs. So that to come to our purpoſe, we haue in this Text two things obſeruable, the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of a Chriſtian, the victorie of faith; the ground of that triumph, the loue of Chriſt, The victorie of faith makes vs more the conquerors, wee obtaine that victorie through him that loued vs. Our obſeruation
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3745:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhall bee none other than the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles owne aſſertion: That the elect of God his owne peculiar, haue this prerogatiue (a matter of ſpeciall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme) that howſoeuer they be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with many afflictions and grieuances, yet in all exigences, they winne the day, they atchieue the conqueſt, they are more than conquerors. Or in a word what preſent enemies ſoeuer they haue waging warre againſt them for the heauenly inheritance, they bring them vnder, they doe more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome them. This is the verdict of the diuine ſpirit vttered from the Oracle of truth, in this text. To the explaning whereof two things are to be vnfolded. Firſt, who bee our worldly enemies heere intimated, next, how we may be ſaid to be more than conquerors. The Apoſtle aimes at both: at our enemies in that he ſaith, In all theſe things: at our conqueſt, in that he ſaith, We doe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3745:10"/>
more than ouercome. Our enemies included in the former words, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited in the verſe foregoing, and marſhalled as it were in battell aray, Tribulation, &amp;c. A great troope, I promiſe you; a terrible armie. So that I may well ſay of their number with Iehorams watchman, I ſee a companie, and of their comming, tis like Iehu the ſonne of Nimſhi, for they march furiouſly. And to giue you a view of their ſeuerall forces &amp; proweſſe, in the forefront is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced tribulation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and it doth properly note out vnto vs, all ſuch bodily grieuances and afflictions, as doe offer violence vnto our outward man, and put it to preſſure and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The next is anguiſh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in which ranke doe march all ſuch inward vexations, as doe euen hem in and ſtrayten the ſoule and bring it into a narrow roome, that it wants the vſe of it ſelfe and is brought to it wits end. In the third place is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3745:10"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is as it were a ſeconding of the former forces, by a continuall ſupply of might and malice to aggrauate our grieuance, and to continue our vexation. The next is famine, want of food neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, an enemie that the Wiſeman prayes againſt Prou. 30. of which kind is Nakednes, likewiſe, Want of veſture to couer our ſhame, and keep vs from annoyance, the one being an enemie to the backe, the other to the belly. Vpon theſe two bands followes Peril, and therin all the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that do or may betide vs in this preſent life, and put our ſtate in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard. And the laſt the ſoreſt enemie, is the Sword, all kind of violent death which the godly are put vnto, for the profeſſion of the Lord Ieſus, and the teſtimonie of a good conſcience. Theſe are our enemies which heere are muſtred againſt vs: and infinite more of the like kind, vnto all which the Deuill is the chiefe leader, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3745:11"/>
of the armie, that great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, who puts in vre, the beſt of his policie, and the proofe of his ſtrength to giue vs the foyle. And that wee may ſee by his manner of ordering them, how that he leaues the ſoreſt till the laſt, euen the ſword to diuide aſunder the life and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that if all the former, tribulation, anguiſh, &amp;c. will not bring vs on our knees, yet that may be ſure to ſpeed: and rather than looſe that, we will vndergoe hard conditions. I but may ſome man ſay vnto vs, how is it that Satan himſelfe is not heere ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, ſeeing he is that great Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-maſter, the commander of ſo many Legions, he it is that owes vs all the ſpite, and ſets all theſe a work: but for him all their blowes were but fleabytings, eaſily awarded; all their plots but like Sampſons bonds eaſily broken. The anſwer is that Satan is not heere excluded. Hee is not like thoſe careleſſe Kings that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3745:11"/>
will lie at home, and ſend their Leiuetenants; not like Dauid ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing vppon his Pallace, when as Ioab is in the brunt of the battell; nor like Senacherib in his Temple at home, when his Captaines be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching abroad: he is alwaies at hand in the forefront, &amp; in the rereward, in the midſt, and at either wing, but the reaſon as I take it, why he is not here expreſſed, is, becauſe his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare is ſpiritual, and not ſo eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it ſelfe, but is manifeſt vnto vs, in theſe his ſoldiers, and 2. in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our meanneſſe and fooliſh diſpoſition, who do vſually ſtand in more dread, of theſe his attendants, then of Satan himſelfe. Whereas on the contrary, we ſhould learne this ſpirituall wiſdome, a ſpeciall point of military diſcipline, not ſo much to looke at theſe things as puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſin, for ſo the ſting of them is taken away in Chriſt, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as they are Satans Ianizaries,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3745:12"/>
his accomplices in whom he ſeeks to worke our ruine, to depriue vs of the hope that we haue here in God, and of the happineſſe that hereafter we expect in heauen. And thus you ſee beloued, what fellowes they be, that we are to grapple withall, we had need to be no children that muſt go to this geare, if theſe be they whom we muſt conquer. Why but you will ſay, is it poſſible that euer we ſhould deale with ſuch as theſe? is ther any hope that euer we ſhould get the victory of ſuch aduerſaries? who cannot be hurt themſelus? they are impenetrable, all the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger lights vpon vs: if any body go to the wall, tis we, if any body catch the foile, it muſt needs be we. yea, indeed are ye at that point? nay but by your leaue S. Paule telleh vs an other tale, the diuine ſpirit will giue vs better hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for he ſaith heere that we are conquerors already. Conquerors? yea more then conquerors, through
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3745:12"/>
him that loued vs. yea will you ſay, and you can proue vs that point, it is ſome thing, it is a matter worth the talking of, if you could aſſure vs of the victorie, before we goe into the field, you would put ſome life and and ſpirit into vs. Well (beloued) me thinkes you may eaſily bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of this, if wee had no more ſuretie but the promiſe of the diuine Spirit, the warrant of this Scripture, tis ſufficient to giue vs encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Suppoſe that two men were going into the field to reuenge their priuat wrongs, and a third man that had the maſtry and commaund of them both, in ſo much that he could bid them giue ouer when hee will, hold their hands at his owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo that neither of them could ſtrike a ſtroke beyond his deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and this man ſhould ſay to one of them, be not diſmayd, but haue a good heart, for I will ſtand by thee, and hee ſhall not giue thee a blow to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3745:13"/>
do thee hurt, nor ſtrike a ſtroke but as I think good, but as for thee I wil giue thee thy free ſcope to doe thy beſt, thou ſhalt aſſuredly giue him the foyle, would this man now doubt of the victorie? would hee be afraid to meet his foe in the very face? O, fy, no, he would goe with courage and reſolution, and why? why? becauſe the victorie is promiſed him. Why (beloued) the Lord hath Satan in his power, he is at his becke, all theſe his follwers are at the Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Further then he permits they can neither ſtrike nor ſtirre, but as he ſayes to the Sea, ſtay thy proud waues, and to the deuouring Angell hold thine hand, tis enough, ſo if he but ſpeak the word, theſe haue done, not a word, nor a blow. Now this Lord heere of this power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, hee promiſeth he will ſtand by vs, hee aſſures vs we ſhall haue the conqueſt, hee ſends vs word ſo from heauen by his ſpirit, ſpeaking
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3745:13"/>
in the Apoſtle. Why? ſhall wee doubt now? ſhal we diſtruſt the iſſue and euent? vndoubtedly, if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not we doe, for as he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth hath ſealed that God is true, ſo hee that denyeth credence to the promiſe, denyeth credit to God. O then let our faith embrace this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and we are ſure. All things are poſſible to him that belieueth. When the people of God were to wage warre with their enemies, and came to God for counſell, if he ſaid but once goe vp, they were preſently all in armes, yea ſo reſolute were they vpon this aſſurance, that when they were to fight againſt their brethren of Beniamin, for the reuenge of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious villanie, Iud. 20.28. and two daies before had had the foile throw their owne raſhneſſe in ill handling a good cauſe: yet the third day when the Lord bad them go vp with hope of victorie, they readily obeyed and ſutably ouercame them. Would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3745:14"/>
they put their affiance in God for bodily victorie, and ſhall not we rely vpon him for a ſpirituall conqueſt? Was hee then a God of his word in meaner affaires, and ſhall he not now be truſted in greater employments? Far be it from vs beloued, the Lord being the ſame in power, in loue, in fidelitie: being able by his power, willing by his loue, and faithfull in his promiſe, that wee ſhould either deny his power, diſclaime his loue, or call his fidelitie into queſtion, ſeeing he hath heere affirmed, we ſhall bee conquerors; elſe where aſſured, that hel gates ſhal not preuaile againſt vs, and daily giues vs experiment of his ſpeciall aide and aſſiſtance, and of the victorie of faith, which bringeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfoot all worldly encumbrances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But that we may giue more euidence to this truth, let vs take a view of it in the experiment of Gods Saints, and let vs ſee how in cloſing with theſe our enemies wee get the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3745:14"/>
and all the Apoſtle heere tels vs, we do more than conquer. It were well, if we might but ouercome, and that we are ſure of, for our faith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercomes the world, and it quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth all the fierie darts of the deuil, giues them a recoyle, and him a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traite. For if we ſtand to it, he runs away, if we reſiſt him, he flies from vs, and when the Captaine is gone, theſe fellowes are like the Philiſtims, they will either runne after him, or turne to our ſide and helpe vs to war againſt him. But that we ſhould not ouercome onely, but be more than conquerors, this is the preheminence of a Chriſtian ſouldier aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warriours. But may that bee, may ſome ſay? I anſwer, we may be ſaid, to be more than conquerors in 4. reſpects, which I wiſh you to take notice of as worthy obſeruation. 1. In that before wee enter into the liſts, wee are ſure of the victorie: worldly conquerors we know, are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3745:15"/>
not ſure of the day, before they goe to the field, they are not ſure of the victorie, till they ſee the end: and therefore if Achab threaten Mica, it muſt be but with yffs &amp; ands: if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne in peace, then Mica muſt pay for the pinnes. If Rabſhake will needs dominere ouer Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſound the retraite before the Alarme, hee ſhall be taught to know, that his tongue was a little more haſtie then his wit, for the iſſue of war is doubtfull, and he that puts on his armour, may not exult, as he that puts it off. But we (beloued) that march vnder Chriſts banner, haue this priuiledge aboue al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Martialiſts, that we are ſure of the victorie, before the fight, we are ſure to returne with Triumph and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme at leaſt for the finall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. Inſomuch that that which the old Iſraelites had ſometime aſſured by diuine verdict, we haue alwaies aſſured by the vertue of the promiſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3745:15"/>
and the current of the couenant of Grace. The truth whereof is moſt apparant, In that Chriſt our Capt: hath ſubdued their forces, he our head hath led them in Triumph, this conqueſt is appropriated to vs, the like victorie according to our Model is merited for vs. The power of his ſtrength is daily at hand to giue vs ſtrength, to affoord vs aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to infuſe courage, &amp; adde dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie, how we may handle our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual armour, how we may take our foes at aduantage, and how we may beſt giue them recoyle. So that, that which is counted meere folly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, in Chriſtianitie is held a point of wiſe reſolution, vz. to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph before the victorie: for before the victorie, we are ſure to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, &amp; in this ſurely more than conquerors. 2. We are more than conquerors in this, that we who eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie way are ſo ſilly and ſimple, of ſo meane forces, and ſo litle power, doe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3745:16"/>
obtaine the victorie. In earthly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, we know the victorie is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obtayned by valiant and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Spirits, great Commanders, and experienced ſouldiers, as the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of Dauid, the ſonnes of Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiah, but here it is far otherwiſe. We that are very earth-wormes, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt of the world, in the hands of all theſe grieuous aduerſaries, Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, anguiſh, &amp;c. euen as Lambs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the rauenous creatures, as little Dauid before that Gyant-like Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah: we, I ſay, that are ſo vnequall matches, we breake through all their forces like the three mightie men through the hoſt of the Philiſtims: they be all ſubdued vnto vs, death it ſelfe the laſt enemie is turned into life, Bethmaueth into Bethel, the doore of death into the gate of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. So that a Chriſtian lying in the agonie and anguiſh thereof, and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſmall ſolace in regard of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igent, when it pleaſeth the Lord to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3745:16"/>
open the eyes of his ſoule, by deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it from the priſon of his bodie, as he did Iacob from his dreame, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the field, he may well ſay with that holy man, This is the houſe of God, and I was not aware, this is none other then the very gate of heauen. But to our purpoſe (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) If you ſhould ſee a little boy, bicker with a mighty Giant, of great ſtrength and puiſſance, and that he ſhould bring him vnder, giue him the ouerthrow and quite vanquiſh him, would ye not ſay, the child were more than a conqueror? Surely the Iſraelites thought ſo of Dauid, and ſutably they gaue him an eminent and ſuperlatiue applauſe in their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant gratulation, Saul hath ſlain his thouſand, and Dauid his ten thouſand. Why euen ſo it is with vs, we that are thus weake and feeble and vnweldie to ſee too, that haue neither forme nor beautie in vs, nor any thing to be deſired, we obtaine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3745:17"/>
the victorie. And that God, who doth by the fooliſhneſſe of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching confound the wiſedome of the wiſe, by the weake and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed things of the world, make the ſtrong to ſtoope and lay their honour in the duſt, and their port in obliuion, that God (I ſay) perfits his owne ſtrength in our weaknes, &amp; aſſiſts vs ſo with the ſufficiencie of his grace, that we may well be ſaid to be more then conquerors. Againe we are more then conquerors, in that by euery victory we grow the ſtronger, yea by euery foil we grow the more puiſſant. Worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors (we know) tho they win the victory, yet it is vſually with the loſſe of much blood, their forces are long time after much weake, and therfore the leſſe vnable to bicker a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. But we (beloued) get the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by all theſe brunts, we get more ſtrength by all our incounters, not in experiment only, but likewiſe in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3745:17"/>
ability, if not ſomtimes for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent yet alwaies in time conuenient. If we be in tribulation, why Peter telleth vs it bringeth forth patience, and patience experience, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hope, and hope maketh vs to lay faſter hould vpon God, and to hould vp our heads with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. So that for one affliction we get fower vertues, for one enimie fower aſociats; for tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we are armed with the buckler of patienc, the breſtplate of experience the helmet of hope, and the ſhield of faith, and what looſers then are we by the bargaine? are we in afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, why Dauid will tell vs it was good for him that he was afflicted, for therby he learned to keep Gods law. Did not he get good ſtrength? before he could not make ſtraight ſteps to Gods ſtatutes. But he was fetting byaſſes and compaſſes, hee went limping and ill fauouredly in the way to heauen, but now, now
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3745:18"/>
he had learned to goe vpright, and to runne with cheerefulneſſe, and ſo ſhall we doe (beloued) if our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions bee ſanctified vnto vs. Are wee reuiled and perſecuted for the name of Chriſt and the profeſſion of his trueth? why Chriſt tells vs we are happy and bleſſed. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles thought they were highly dignified, yea ſtrangely preferred, that they were thought worthy to ſuffer any thing for the name of Chriſt. And ſurely it is an high dignitie, to be a Captaine as it were againſt Satan, and to breake a ſpeare, in the cauſe of Chriſt. For this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement wee get by it, that whereas before we were aſhamed of the name of Chriſt, we were afraid to profeſſe the truth, now we are as bold as Lyons, and as reſolute as may be in the cauſe of God. Peter that before durſt not looke a ſilly wench in the face, but would ſweare and lye, rather than he would take
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3745:18"/>
notice of Chriſt, is now of ſo coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a ſpirit, that he dare euen ſtand for him to the very face of the high Prieſt and the Elders. Is Paul in bonds and impriſonment for the Goſpell? why that gaines freedome to the Goſpell, and makes it famous euen in Neroes court. Is Lazarus ready to ſtarue for hunger, and in the faintneſſe of his ſpirit does hee giue vp the ghoſt? I, but what loſeth he by that? what looſeth he? nay he is a great gainer, for hee comes ſo much the ſooner to heauen, for death the Lord of our enemies is ſwallowed vp in victorie. I, it is made a paſſage of life, being paſt it, we are out of all gun-ſhot, for then for euer we are conquerors, our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ſhal be celebrated to eternity, the greater danger the more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous victorie, thus wee are likewiſe more than conquerors. Laſtly, wee may bee ſaid to bee more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, in that, when we ſeeme to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3745:19"/>
be ouercome, and all men deeme we haue the foile, why then haue we the day, then doe we celebrate the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, then wee may ſing with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah, O my ſoule thou haſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched valiantly. This is eſpecially ſeene in death, when as that fearefull Combatant, that gaſtly Aduerſarie, aſſailes vs, and ſets vpon vs, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee will inſtance onely in that, and ſhew you, how euen in death, when we are laid full low, why then is our Triumph at the higheſt, our Conqueſt is moſt ſupereminent. A ſtrange concluſion to humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but an euident truth to the eye of faith. For when as the godly are brought once to this paſſe, that the wicked haue bereaued them of their liues, O, then they thinke all is well, they are rid of them, they haue now brought them vnder. So the Deuill thought, and hee could get Chriſt nayled to the croſſe once, all was well, nay, but and if he be laid in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3745:19"/>
graue once, and the ſtone ſealed vp, all is ſure, there will be no more tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of him, vnleſſe it be in diſgrace, to call him a deceiuer, who ſaid, he would riſe within three daies, but could not, and therfore there would be no more doings, vnleſſe his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſhould come and ſteale him away by night, to gull the people. But they would watch them for that, they would ſet ſouldiers to keepe the Tombe, and ſee who durſt be ſo bold, as to come and ſtirre it. Thus the Deuill and his impes did euen dance as it were vpon the graue of Chriſt, and fetch their friskes and Moriſcoes as it were, ſinging as it is in the Pſalme: Surely hee is now ſo low, he can neuer riſe againe. Thus they trampled vpon him, as vpon a dead Lion, but the mightie Lion of the Tribe of Iudah, roſe valiantly from the dead, grappled with that mightie Dragon and ouerthrew him: and like that valiant Sampſon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3745:20"/>
caried the gates of Azzah, the gates of death vpon his backe in triumph, ſo that they are now no more the gates of death, but the gates of life, whereby all the godly enter into glory. So that if the Deuill come vnto Gods children and tell them, skin for skin, and all that a man hath will he giue for his life, they may tell him he lyes, for if it ſo pleaſed God, they had rather giue all they haue to be rid of their life. If I ſhould here enlarge my ſpeech, to relate the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and confidence, and reioyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the conſtant Martyrs and faithfull witneſſes of the Lord Ieſus haue had, in ſuffering for his truth, I might liuely paint out vnto you, more than a conqueſt. Steuen vnder the ſtones ſees heauen open, and Chriſt at his Fathers right hand, ready to receiue him: the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whereof did euen ſo ſolace his Soule, that hee laid downe his life with ſolace, ſhowing greater valour
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3745:20"/>
in bearing the blowes, then they crueltie, in their enraged malice. We read in the ſtories of the Church, of a young man that was put to the racke, for the profeſſion of Chriſt, and being kept vpon it with much torture from morning to noone, hee lay all the while quietly, with a ſweet ſmiling countenance, as one that had been in a pleaſant ſlumber: which being much admired, when he was deliuered from the racke, it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, whether he felt no paine all the while, becauſe his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was ſo cheerefull, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red indeed that hee did feele ſome paine, but all the while (as hee thought) there ſtood by him a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull yoong man, who wyped the ſweat off his face alwayes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled him with cold water, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the paine was greatly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laied, and it was not ſo much, when he was on the Racke, as after he was taken off. How euer all the godly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3745:21"/>
haue not ſuch extraordinarie appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions; yet they haue the power of Chriſt ſupporting their weakneſſe, and the preſence of the ſpirit, giuing them courage and abilitie, to beare all with courage that is laid vpon them, for the name of Chriſt. I might giue many inſtances of rare conſtancie in this our Land, in the time of Queene Mary, in which the Lords people did euen after a ſort ſeeme lauiſh of their bloud, to ſhed it for the witneſſing of the Lord Ieſus, who had not ſpared to ſhed his hearts bloud for them. Who all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ayded by Gods ſpeciall aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, did breake through all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and freely gaue their liues for the Goſpell, and therein became more than conquerors, in that being conquered, they conquered, yea in that they ſeemed to bee ouercome, therein ſtood the very glory of their victorie: for that ſame Chriſtian va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour the Lord had put into them, it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3745:21"/>
made them reſolue to cleaue to Chriſt in life and in death, to make him their portion. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe excellent is that ſpeech of that Reuerend Hooper, laying out vnto vs the combat betweene the frailtie of the fleſh, and the reſolution of the ſpirit: and letting vs ſee how the grace of God preuailes, againſt the diſgraces and greeuances of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Impriſonment (ſaith he) is pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but yet libertie vpon bad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is more painfull. The priſons ſtinke: I but not ſo much as ſweet houſes, where the feare of God is wanting. I but we muſt be alone and ſolitarie: why it is better to be ſo, and haue God with thee, then to be in companie with the wicked. Loſſe of goods is great: But the loſſe of Gods fauour and grace is greater. I, but I am a poore ſimple creature and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how to anſwer, before ſuch a great ſort of noble, learned, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3745:22"/>
wiſe: It is better to make anſwer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the pompe and pride of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, then to ſtand naked in the ſight of all heauen and earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iuſt God at the latter day. Why, but I ſhall die then by the hands of the cruell man? Why he is bleſſed, yea a thouſand times happy, that loſeth this life full of mortall miſeries, and findeth the life full of eternall Ioyes.</q> Thus (beloued) the holy ones of God haue reſolued to lay downe their liues for the Lord Ieſus, and in looſing their liues, they haue found them, for they haue found Chriſt the life of their ſoules, according to his promiſe, He that loſeth his life for my ſake ſhall find it, and haue they not then been vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant conquerors? yes vndoubtedly more than conquerors. The vſe of all this that hath been ſaid, is, to let vs ſee the excellencie of a Chriſtian, and what a priuiledge it is to be the child of God, for euery ſtate is ſanctified
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3745:22"/>
vnto vs, and we thereby are brought nearer vnto God, and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to reioice, continually to ſolace our ſelues in the Lord, and in him to cheere vp our ſpirits in euery condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, knowing, that the moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous eſtate we can be in, is ſanctified vnto vs, and that when God lets any croſſes betide vs, why it is becauſe he hath ſome good to worke vnto vs out of them, either that hee may thereby curbe ſome ſinne, and ſo driue the Cananites out of his owne Inheritance, or elſe that he may giue vs ſcope to exerciſe the graces wee haue receiued, and ſo to make vs more nimble and actiue, more poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke and experienced againſt a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encounter. And therefore wee ſhould not be ſo timorous and faint-hearted, as we be, at the very hearing of any affliction comming toward vs, like the Iſraelites running away at the very ſight of Goliah, no, wee ſhould plucke vp our hearts, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3745:23"/>
cheere vp our ſpirits, knowing that the greateſt of our aduerſaries is but an obiect for vs to ſhew out valour vpon, and to make proofe of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall puiſſance. Why, what care I how ſtout mine aduerſarie be? what doe I feare how ſtrong an arme hee hath, or what a big legge or how well appointed he come, when as I know I ſhall ouercome him? The ſtouter he is, and the better weapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hee comes, the more ſhall be my glory, for I know (relying vpon God) I ſhall giue him the foyle, and therefore the better he is appointed, the gladder I am. Thus ſhould our hearts riſe within vs, and euen leape for ioy, that we may haue an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to ſhew our loue to Chriſt, and to beare a ſtroke for his ſake. And therfore if God ſhould call any of vs to greater triall, euen to looſe our liues for his truth, yet ſtill wee ſhould reioyce, knowing, that the greater the outward greeuance is,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3745:23"/>
the more neere it brings vs to God: and that God vnto whom it brings vs, is ſo gratious, that where our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and combat is the greater, he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies and ſeconds, yea and doubles his ſtrength the power of his ſpirit. And againe tis a ſpeciall prerogatiue, and an high grace for a Chriſtian, that God ſhall chuſe him out before many others, as a ſpeciall man, to be a Captaine as it were, and one of the worthies of Iſrael, to venter further for the Lord, than a great many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall doe, and to combat and bicker with the Deuill, euen at his owne weapon, his owne life. And it is the Cup likewiſe our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour begun to vs of, why who would not bee glad to pledge him? me thinkes hee ſhould thinke himſelfe highly graced, that may haue the firſt and the fulleſt draught, for this is a true drinking of an holy health, a ſpeciall potion for the health of our ſoules. And laſtly,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3745:24"/>
what a bleſſing is it, to haue thoſe things which are puniſhments of ſinne, turned into witneſſings and teſtifications of the truth of God, to be a grace and a glory and an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament to the Goſpell of Chriſt? And for the hurt, that afflictions can doe vs, why we muſt know they are but like the furnace of Babilon, which burnt not the three children, no, not ſo much as ſcorched not the hayre of their heads, but only loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their bandes. So all the hurt that afflictions do vs, is, but to looſe the bands of our corruption, to purge and purifie vs from our ſinnes, a moſt happy loſſe. A child ſeeing his Father cut a grape from the vine, lookes at it, and it ſeemes very prety vnto him, hee thinks it were pitie it ſhould be preſt; for then tis ſpoild: but the wiſe Father knowes that ſtamped it is the beſt, for if it ſhould be let alone, it would not preſently: but being preſſed it wil yeeld it own
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3745:24"/>
blood, that comfortable liquor which cheares the heart of man. Such children and fooles are we, we thinke if wee might ſerue God in peace and quietneſſe, without any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, all were well, whereas God our wiſe Father knowes if wee were let alone, we would be naught, we would rot in our corruptions, and therefore in his wiſedome hee lets vs be ſtamped in the wine preſſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, that wee may be made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his minde, ſuch as may euen cheate his heart, and ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of conſtancie, as may euen draw vs on to the embracing of the truth. For the bloud of Martyrs hath been the ſeed of the Church, and neuer did the Church flouriſh ſo much as in time of perſecution. But alas poore ſilly ſoules that wee are, what cowardly hearts haue we? if a man giue vs but a diſgracefull tearme, wee are ready with thoſe Diſciples, Ioh. 6. to leaue Chriſt, to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3745:25"/>
follow him no more. What a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly part is this to caſt away our weapons before we haue any blow? why we ſhould reioice we are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to ſuffer any thing for Chriſt, and wee ſhould perſuade our ſelues, that he that giues vs power to beare that, he will afterward giue vs courage to endure an harder brunt. And as for the wicked that delight in the perſecuting and diſgracing of the Saints of God, let them learne hence what fooles they are, for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they thinke, they doe the worſt that can bee to Gods children, in mocking them, in diſgracing them, the truth is, they could not do them a greater pleaſure, for by this means, they make them more than conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: by this means they make them atcheiue a moſt glorious victorie, for let them know, that howſoeuer they can diſcerne nothing in the Saints of God but miſerie and baſeneſſe, and a life worthy to bee lothed, yet the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3745:25"/>
truth is that when they ſeem to them to bee at the loweſt ebbe, then are they indeed in the ſight of God, and in the feeling of their owne ſoules moſt glorious conquerors: inſomuch that, (as one ſaith well) Contraries may euen be predicated of them at the ſame inſtant, and that they may well be ſaid to be, the fouleſt, and the faireſt, the pooreſt &amp; the richeſt, the fooliſheſt and the wiſeſt, the higheſt and the loweſt, the baſeſt and yet the nobleſt, the weakeſt &amp; the ſtrongeſt. They are the fouleſt in that to the worlds eye, there is neither form nor beauty in them: and yet the faireſt, for they are the ſpouſe of Chriſt, his faire one, his loue, his doue, his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the Kings daughter that is all glorious within. The pooreſt they be, for they vſe this world as though they vſed it not, and yet the richeſt, for they haue laid vp treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. The fooliſheſt, for ſuch God chuſeth to confound the wiſdom of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3745:26"/>
the wiſe, and yet the wiſeſt, for the feare of the Lord is true wiſdom, and to flee from euill the chiefe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. They be the baſeſt, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deemed, the very refuſe and off-ſcouring of the world: and yet the nobleſt being the ſonnes of God, the heyrs of heauen. They are the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt as being continually exerciſed with tribulation, anguiſh, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, perill and ſword: and yet the ſtrongeſt, for in all theſe we are more than conquerors, through him that loued vs. So that me thinks, if it were for nothing elſe, then this, the wicked ſhould ceaſe to perſecute Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, namely, becauſe by this means, they greatly aduance them, they make them moſt glorious victors. I know there is neuer a wicked perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting man, but he would be loth to do any good to Gods children: if he knew any thing that would further their preferment, he would be ſure to reape it from them, if it lay in his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3745:26"/>
power: why then what a foole art thou to perſecute them? thou doſt by this means, make the graces of Gods ſpirit to ſhine more eminent in them thou giueſt them occaſions to maſter their corruptions, ſo that they are conquerors both ouer thee &amp; them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and get more ſtrength and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſance daily, fight more couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vnder the banner of Chriſt, &amp; ſhall haue more garlands &amp; wreaths of renowme ſet vpon their heads, then if they had not gone through thoſe brunts. So that in ſteed of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them hurt, thou doeſt them a great pleaſure, making them heere to grow in grace like the Palme, which the more it is preſſed, the faſter it ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, &amp; heereafter to expect a greater glory, for he that ouercomes with courage ſhall be crowned with Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and haue thoſe ſpeciall prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minences that enſue ſuch a conqueſt. What hurt therefore canſt thou doe vnto vs? who euer thou art, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3745:27"/>
to be doing with the Saints of God. What hurt? nay thou doſt vs much good, for thy curſes are turned into bleſſings, there is neither ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie nor witchcraft againſt Iacob, and as Salomon ſayes, the very mercies of the wicked are cruelty; ſo we may well inuert the ſpeech, and ſay, that the crueltie of the wicked is mercy, through his mercy who hath loued vs, for wee are onely conquerors through him that loued vs. A word of which and ſo an end. The power of this victorie is from Chriſt, all our ſufficiencie is from him, by faith it is that we receiue it, his ſpirit infuſing that courage into vs, that makes vs play the men, and winne the field. His loue was the cauſe of all this good, for his loue to vs made him leaue heauen, the ſeat of his glory, &amp; to deſcend to the earth, the footſtool of miſerie, and there to fight that ſame firſt bloudy field, and to giue Satan the foyle, ſince which time Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3745:27"/>
could neuer finally ouercome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his choſen. Well then belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued did Chriſt come into the world to make vs conquerors? Did he deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from heauen, that hee might giue vs the victorie ouer all theſe enemies, Tribulation, Perſecution, &amp;c. I that he did, our text ſayes ſo. And doe wee now celebrate the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of that comming, the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Natiuitie? I that wee do, for now is the time of that ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Why then my beloued wee muſt remember, ſo to keep this time of ſolemnitie, that we ſtill retayn our victorie, that we ſtill keepe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt that Chriſt hath purchaſed, for elſe it were a right mock-holy-day indeed, to celebrate the time of Chr: comming into the world, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue our ſelues of the end wherfore he came, of the benefit we reap by his comming. His end was, ſayes my text to make vs conquerors of all theſe our enemies, Tribul: Anguiſh,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3745:28"/>
&amp;c. this was his end. We muſt then take heed, that we do not againe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue our ſelues, to the commiſſion, to the entertainment of ſuch ſins, as may bring all theſe enemies in vpon vs againe, iuſtly for our ſinne, and ſubiect vs vnto them. If a Towne or a Citie ſhould keep a feſtiuall day in the memorie of ſome great victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, their King had got, in the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their enemies, and ſhould in the meane time ſend for thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that the King had put to flight, &amp; bring them into the City, and not only ſo, but vrge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the banquet, &amp; reioyce with them, &amp; in them, and bid them welcome, and make them good cheere, and let them take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it againe, would the King take this well thinke ye? would hee thinke it were a good remembrance of his venturing of his life for the ſafetie of that city? well quoth he; why it would ſo incenſe and enrage his ſpirits againſt them, that hee
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3745:28"/>
could not hold his hands, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently as it is in the Goſpell: hee would ſend forth his warriours, to ſlay thoſe traitours and burne vp their city. Why thus the caſe ſtands with vs beloued. Chriſt our King the King of peace and glory, came downe from heauen to deliuer vs from the power of hell, from all our enemies, hee got the victory with valour, we now celebrate the time of his comming to conquer, if wee ſhall now celebrate it in paſſing the time, and ſolacing our ſelues with thoſe ſins, that he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, as intemperance, idleneſſe wanton paſtims, if we ſend for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, that he hath ſubdued, and giue them poſſeſſion againe, why what do we els but loſe the victory, caſhiere Chriſts conqueſt and mock his bloudſhed? And what may we then look for but the fearful doome before named, that as we haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled thoſe traitors in ſinne, ſo we
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3745:29"/>
may drinke as deepe of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? O therefore beloued, let vs be wiſe, let our reioycing be ſuch as we may fit the time, ſpirituall reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, let our mirth be ſuch as may ſtand with our victory, ſpirituall mirth, not fooliſh laughter, which is madneſſe or worſe, not ieſting and iybing which becomes not Saints, not vnclean ſpeeches, which ſhould not once be named among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not winter tales, and fooliſh ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the diuels chronicles, which neuer need printing we can ſo well remember them. Wherefore let vs rather beloued, cheere vp our ſoules in the ſpirituall memory of Chriſts victory, of the victory of faith that ouercomes the world. In the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues of Chriſtianity, which are moſt ſingular, yet ſo that we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies refer them to him that loued vs, for we only enioy them through him that loued vs. Let vs pray. &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
